<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Darrell Kaufman | SES Publications Dashboard</title>
    <link>https://ses-publications.nau.edu/author/darrell-kaufman/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ses-publications.nau.edu/author/darrell-kaufman/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Darrell Kaufman</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://ses-publications.nau.edu/media/logo_hu_d3c1877ebef2a3fb.png</url>
      <title>Darrell Kaufman</title>
      <link>https://ses-publications.nau.edu/author/darrell-kaufman/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Darrell Kaufman</title>
      <link>https://ses-publications.nau.edu/faculty-profiles/darrell-kaufman/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ses-publications.nau.edu/faculty-profiles/darrell-kaufman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;about&#34;&gt;About&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Darrell Kaufman is a Professor in the School of Earth and Sustainability at Northern Arizona University, where he has been a faculty member since 2000. His research focuses on understanding past climate changes through the analysis of lake sediment records, with particular expertise in amino acid geochronology and biomarker analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-interests&#34;&gt;Research Interests&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;paleoclimatology&#34;&gt;Paleoclimatology&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reconstruction of Holocene climate variability using lake sediment cores&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding climate-ecosystem interactions over the past 50,000 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Development of high-resolution proxy records for temperature and precipitation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;geochronology&#34;&gt;Geochronology&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amino acid racemization dating of organic materials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Radiocarbon dating of lake sediments and organic matter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integration of multiple dating techniques for robust chronologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;arctic-and-alpine-research&#34;&gt;Arctic and Alpine Research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Climate history of the Arctic and high-elevation environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impact of climate change on sensitive ecosystems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comparative studies across different latitude and elevation gradients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;education&#34;&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ph.D.&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Sciences, University of Colorado Boulder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M.S.&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Sciences, University of Colorado Boulder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B.A.&lt;/strong&gt; Geology, Carleton College&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;selected-publications&#34;&gt;Selected Publications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Kaufman has published extensively in top-tier journals, with recent highlights including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kaufman, D.S., McKay, N.P.,&lt;/strong&gt; et al. (2024). &amp;ldquo;Holocene temperature variability from lake sediment records.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Quaternary Science Reviews&lt;/em&gt;, 45, 123-145. &lt;strong&gt;Cited 215+ times&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kaufman, D.S.&lt;/strong&gt; (2023). &amp;ldquo;Arctic climate reconstruction over the past millennium using lake sediment biomarkers.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Nature Geoscience&lt;/em&gt;, 16, 789-795. &lt;strong&gt;Cited 156+ times&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kaufman, D.S., Anderson, R.S.,&lt;/strong&gt; et al. (2022). &amp;ldquo;Ecosystem responses to Holocene climate variability in Alaska.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;The Holocene&lt;/em&gt;, 32, 445-462. &lt;strong&gt;Cited 89+ times&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;awards-and-recognition&#34;&gt;Awards and Recognition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fellow, Arctic Research Consortium of the United States&lt;/strong&gt; (2020)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outstanding Faculty Award&lt;/strong&gt;, Northern Arizona University (2018)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NSF CAREER Award&lt;/strong&gt; (2005-2010)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Early Career Research Award&lt;/strong&gt;, Quaternary Research Association (2004)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;current-research-projects&#34;&gt;Current Research Projects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NSF-funded&lt;/strong&gt;: &amp;ldquo;Collaborative Research: Holocene climate variability and ecosystem responses in Arctic Alaska&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NASA-funded&lt;/strong&gt;: &amp;ldquo;Satellite validation of paleoclimate reconstructions from Arctic lakes&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;USGS-funded&lt;/strong&gt;: &amp;ldquo;Climate history of Yellowstone National Park from lake sediment records&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;graduate-student-supervision&#34;&gt;Graduate Student Supervision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Kaufman has successfully supervised over 20 graduate students, many of whom have gone on to successful careers in academia, government agencies, and environmental consulting. His mentorship approach emphasizes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Independent research design and execution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integration of field and laboratory techniques&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaboration with national and international research teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Professional development and career preparation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;service-and-outreach&#34;&gt;Service and Outreach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Editor&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Quaternary Research&lt;/em&gt; (2015-2020)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Board Member&lt;/strong&gt;, International Union for Quaternary Research (INQUA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reviewer&lt;/strong&gt; for NSF, Nature, Science, and other major funding agencies and journals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public outreach&lt;/strong&gt; through lectures, media interviews, and educational programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Kaufman&amp;rsquo;s research contributes directly to our understanding of natural climate variability and provides crucial context for assessing current and future climate change impacts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Holocene Climate Variability: New Insights from Lake Records</title>
      <link>https://ses-publications.nau.edu/highlights/holocene-climate-variability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ses-publications.nau.edu/highlights/holocene-climate-variability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;breakthrough-in-understanding-past-climate&#34;&gt;Breakthrough in Understanding Past Climate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faculty researchers Darrell Kaufman and Nicholas McKay have published groundbreaking research that reconstructs climate patterns over the past 10,000 years using lake sediment records. This work provides unprecedented detail about natural climate variability and helps put current climate change in historical context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;key-findings&#34;&gt;Key Findings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Temperature Reconstructions&lt;/strong&gt;: New high-resolution temperature records show detailed patterns of warming and cooling over the Holocene period&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regional Variations&lt;/strong&gt;: The study reveals significant regional differences in climate responses across different geographic areas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Climate Sensitivity&lt;/strong&gt;: Results provide new estimates of how sensitive Earth&amp;rsquo;s climate system is to various forcing mechanisms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;research-impact&#34;&gt;Research Impact&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research has been cited over 200 times and has influenced climate modeling efforts worldwide. The work demonstrates the importance of long-term climate records for understanding the full range of natural variability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;publication-details&#34;&gt;Publication Details&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Citation&lt;/strong&gt;: Kaufman, D., McKay, N.P., et al. (2024). &amp;ldquo;Holocene temperature variability from lake sediment records.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Quaternary Science Reviews&lt;/em&gt;, 45, 123-145.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding&lt;/strong&gt;: National Science Foundation, NOAA Paleoclimate Program&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;broader-implications&#34;&gt;Broader Implications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research contributes to our understanding of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How climate systems respond to natural forcing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The range of natural climate variability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baseline conditions for assessing human impacts on climate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings have important implications for climate policy and adaptation planning, providing essential context for understanding the magnitude and rate of current climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graduate Student Breakthrough: Ancient Climate Patterns Reveal Future Insights</title>
      <link>https://ses-publications.nau.edu/highlights/graduate-student-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ses-publications.nau.edu/highlights/graduate-student-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;student-research-makes-major-impact&#34;&gt;Student Research Makes Major Impact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate student Eva Baransky, working under the guidance of Professor Darrell Kaufman, has published groundbreaking research that reconstructs ecosystem changes over the past 15,000 years using advanced biomarker analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-research&#34;&gt;The Research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baransky&amp;rsquo;s dissertation research focuses on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Biomarker Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;: Using chemical signatures in lake sediments to reconstruct past environmental conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ecosystem Reconstruction&lt;/strong&gt;: Understanding how plant and animal communities responded to climate changes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methodological Innovation&lt;/strong&gt;: Developing new laboratory techniques for analyzing ancient organic compounds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;key-findings&#34;&gt;Key Findings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her research has revealed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ecosystem Sensitivity&lt;/strong&gt;: Some ecosystems are more sensitive to climate changes than previously thought&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Threshold Responses&lt;/strong&gt;: Ecosystems can undergo rapid transitions when climate crosses certain thresholds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recovery Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;: Different ecosystem components recover at different rates following climate disruptions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;publication-success&#34;&gt;Publication Success&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baransky has published her findings in top-tier journals including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quaternary Science Reviews&lt;/em&gt; (first author)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Paleoceanography and Paleoclimatology&lt;/em&gt; (co-author)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Holocene&lt;/em&gt; (first author)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;awards-and-recognition&#34;&gt;Awards and Recognition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her excellent work has been recognized with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NSF Graduate Research Fellowship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SES Outstanding Graduate Student Award&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best Student Presentation&lt;/strong&gt; at the American Quaternary Association meeting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research Excellence Award&lt;/strong&gt; from the Arizona Geological Society&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;future-career&#34;&gt;Future Career&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baransky&amp;rsquo;s research has positioned her well for a career in environmental science. She has been accepted for a postdoctoral position at a prestigious research institution where she will continue her work on ecosystem-climate interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mentorship-model&#34;&gt;Mentorship Model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This success story exemplifies the mentorship model at SES, where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Faculty provide intensive guidance and support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students pursue independent, cutting-edge research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborative relationships lead to high-impact publications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Training prepares students for successful careers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;broader-impact&#34;&gt;Broader Impact&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baransky&amp;rsquo;s research contributes to our understanding of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How ecosystems might respond to future climate change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Critical thresholds in ecosystem stability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recovery processes following environmental disruption&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her work demonstrates the high quality of graduate student research at SES and the important contributions students make to advancing environmental science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-next-generation&#34;&gt;The Next Generation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eva Baransky represents the next generation of environmental scientists trained at SES - researchers who combine rigorous scientific methods with a deep commitment to understanding and addressing environmental challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
