<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ecohydrology | SES Publications Dashboard</title>
    <link>https://ses-publications.nau.edu/tag/ecohydrology/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ses-publications.nau.edu/tag/ecohydrology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Ecohydrology</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://ses-publications.nau.edu/media/logo_hu_67ed2d5af17cd7c7.png</url>
      <title>Ecohydrology</title>
      <link>https://ses-publications.nau.edu/tag/ecohydrology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abraham Springer</title>
      <link>https://ses-publications.nau.edu/faculty-profiles/abraham-springer/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ses-publications.nau.edu/faculty-profiles/abraham-springer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;about&#34;&gt;About&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Abraham &amp;ldquo;Abe&amp;rdquo; Springer is a Professor of hydrogeology and ecohydrology in the School of Earth and Sustainability at Northern Arizona University, where he has been a faculty member since 2008. His research focuses on understanding the complex relationships between groundwater, surface water, and ecosystem health, with particular emphasis on springs ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-interests&#34;&gt;Research Interests&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;springs-ecology-and-ecohydrology&#34;&gt;Springs Ecology and Ecohydrology&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigation of springs as unique ecosystems and biodiversity hotspots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding groundwater-surface water interactions in spring systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Development of classification systems for springs ecosystems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assessment of spring ecosystem health and function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;climate-change-refugia&#34;&gt;Climate Change Refugia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research on springs as &amp;ldquo;wet refuges&amp;rdquo; for plants and animals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding how groundwater-fed springs buffer against climate-induced drying&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigation of springs as potential climate change refugia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analysis of ecosystem resilience in arid and semi-arid environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;aquifer-health-and-groundwater-resources&#34;&gt;Aquifer Health and Groundwater Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assessment of aquifer conditions and groundwater sustainability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigation of human impacts on groundwater systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding connections between aquifer health and spring ecosystems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Groundwater resource management and conservation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;education&#34;&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ph.D.&lt;/strong&gt; Hydrogeology/Earth Sciences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M.S.&lt;/strong&gt; Hydrology/Water Resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B.S.&lt;/strong&gt; Earth Sciences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-impact&#34;&gt;Research Impact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Springer has made significant contributions to understanding springs ecosystems, with over 1,900 citations of his research. His work has advanced knowledge of how these unique ecosystems function and their critical role in biodiversity conservation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;major-research-contributions&#34;&gt;Major Research Contributions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;springs-classification-system&#34;&gt;Springs Classification System&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developed a geomorphological-based classification system for springs ecosystems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced understanding of springs ecosystem diversity and function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contributed to standardized approaches for springs assessment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;climate-change-refugia-research&#34;&gt;Climate Change Refugia Research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Co-authored influential research published in &lt;em&gt;Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demonstrated the potential for springs to serve as climate refugia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced understanding of ecosystem resilience in changing climates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;regional-springs-assessment&#34;&gt;Regional Springs Assessment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assessed conditions of 200 springs in Coconino and Kaibab National Forests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conducted comprehensive studies of Arizona springs ecosystems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigated water sources for iconic locations like the Grand Canyon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;professional-collaborations&#34;&gt;Professional Collaborations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;springs-stewardship-institute&#34;&gt;Springs Stewardship Institute&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborates with the Springs Stewardship Institute at the Museum of Northern Arizona&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contributes to springs conservation and stewardship initiatives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bridges scientific research with practical conservation applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;federal-land-management&#34;&gt;Federal Land Management&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Works with National Forest Service on springs assessment projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborates with National Park Service on groundwater and springs research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contributes scientific expertise to land management decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-philosophy&#34;&gt;Research Philosophy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Springer emphasizes the critical importance of understanding hydrological connections: &amp;ldquo;All climatic and human-induced changes to hydrologic systems influence the aquifers that supply waters to springs.&amp;rdquo; His work demonstrates how human activities, particularly groundwater pumping, can threaten these unique ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-research-findings&#34;&gt;Key Research Findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;climate-adaptation&#34;&gt;Climate Adaptation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Springs can buffer against short-term climate-influenced drying events&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Groundwater-fed springs provide stability in variable climate conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These ecosystems may be crucial for species survival in increasingly arid environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conservation-concerns&#34;&gt;Conservation Concerns&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Human pumping of aquifers risks drying up springs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spring ecosystems face increasing pressure from climate change and human activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conservation strategies must consider groundwater protection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;graduate-student-supervision&#34;&gt;Graduate Student Supervision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Springer mentors graduate students in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hydrogeology and ecohydrology field techniques&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Springs ecosystem assessment and monitoring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Groundwater-surface water interaction studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Climate change impact analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conservation science applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;professional-service&#34;&gt;Professional Service&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contributor to scientific journals in hydrogeology and ecology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborator with federal and state land management agencies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member of professional organizations in hydrogeology and ecology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advocate for springs conservation and groundwater protection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-impact-on-conservation&#34;&gt;Research Impact on Conservation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Springer&amp;rsquo;s research has direct implications for conservation policy and land management, particularly in the southwestern United States where water resources are increasingly scarce. His work helps inform strategies for protecting these unique ecosystems in a changing climate.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
